<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The descent of authoritie: or, The magistrates patent from heaven Manifested in a sermon preached at Lincolnes assizes, March 13. 1636. By Thomas Hurste Dr. of Divinity, and one of his Majesties chaplains.</title>
            <author>Hurste, Thomas, d. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14007</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840087</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840087</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4558</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4558)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1209:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The descent of authoritie: or, The magistrates patent from heaven Manifested in a sermon preached at Lincolnes assizes, March 13. 1636. By Thomas Hurste Dr. of Divinity, and one of his Majesties chaplains.</title>
                  <author>Hurste, Thomas, d. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Bishop] for Iohn Clark, and are to bee sold at his shop under Saint Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Genesis IX, 6.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The year of the sermon is given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The descent of authority.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4558:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4558:1"/>
            <p>THE DESCENT OF AVTHORITIE: <hi>OR,</hi> THE MAGISTRATES PATENT FROM HEAVEN. Manifeſted in a Sermon preached at <hi>Lincolnes</hi> Aſſizes, <hi>March</hi> 13. 1636.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS HVRSTE Dr. of Divinity, and one of his Majeſties Chaplains.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 13.1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is no power but of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Clark,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop under Saint <hi>Peters Church</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4558:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4558:2"/>
            <head>TO MY VERY NOBLE FRIEND AND WORTHY Patron, Sir WILLIAM SAVILE, Baronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing perſwaded to make this Sermon le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, I preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to uſe your name for the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As it is a favour from you, I make bold to borrow it: and as it is a teſtimony of due reſpect from me, you deſerve it. Go on ſtill in mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting your unfained love to God
<pb facs="tcp:4558:3"/>and his Church, your Prince and Country. And that you may long continue to be (as you are) an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament to your Family, and a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to your friends, ſhall be the prayer of him that is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all hearty affection,<lb/> and due obſervance</hi>
                  <lb/> THO. HVRSTE.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Lednam</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iune</hi> 1. 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Perlegi Concionem hanc, cui titulus eſt</hi> (The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of Authority &amp;c.) <hi>nec in eâ quicquam reperio quò minùs cum utilitate publicâ imprimatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sa: Baker.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex aedibus Londin.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iunij</hi> 14. 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4558:3"/>
            <head>THE DESCENT OF AVTHORITIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gen. 9.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Whoſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood bee ſhed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Divine may ſpeake of ſuch Texts of Scripture, that it may bee ſaid as it was to hin that ſpake of <hi>Hercules</hi> his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Quis eum vituperat?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plutar. Apoph. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ac.</note> as if that were to light a candle in the Sun-ſhine. So when we Preachers ſpeake of death, mortality, Gods mercy, mans proneneſſe to ſinne, &amp;c. Some may ſay or thinke, <hi>Who doubts of this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for this Diſcourſe that I am to ſpeake of, the juſt power of one man over another, it may ſeeme to be Apocryphall, or an Exchecker-chamber caſe.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4558:4"/>Some (eſpecially inferiours) thinke that one ſhould bee as good as another: that as wee were at our births, and ſhall be at our deaths; ſo in our lives we ſhould bee equall. Being Chriſtian brethren in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and partaking of the ſame Sacraments: ſo (Anabap<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſtically) we ſhould bee in Politicks; and the pearching of one man above another is but hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane invention and commanding policy. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſome inferiours are willing to obey principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for feare of puniſhment, little for conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>To ſatisfie us all then, that the ſuperiority of one man over another is no humane uſurpation, but a divine inſtitution; not upheld only by the ſhores, or underlaid with the bolſters of mans device, but hath the foundation of Gods appointment: take notice how that God who hath made in Heaven Angels and Archangels, in the Firmament the King the Sun, the Queene the Moone, and the common people the Starres; in the Aire the Eagle and the Flie; in the Sea the Whale and the Herring; upon Earth the Lyon and the Graſſehopper, hils and val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, leas and furrowes: the ſame God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt men, ſome like the Centurion, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9.</note> and others as the Centurions ſervant, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to obey: as in ſtature ſome higher like the <hi>Anakims,</hi> and ſome lower as <hi>Zacheus.</hi> Thus God hath ordered, that <hi>Whoſo ſheds mans blood,</hi> muſt not be reprieved till the day of Judgement, or bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed miraculouſly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 12.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37 36.</note> as <hi>Herod</hi> was, by an Angel ſent from Heaven; or as in <hi>Sennacheribs</hi> Hoſt, where an Angel came and ſlew the Hoſt, but <hi>by man,</hi> and not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4558:4"/>by Angels <hi>ſhall a malefactors blood bee ſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then is <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or High Commiſſion under the great Seale of Heaven directed to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates. Here is DEVS REGI: for ſo he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, DIEV ET MON DROIT. And then (give me leave to ſay a piece of your Commiſſion before you goe to the Hall) from hence it followeth, CAROLVS (but DEI GRATIA) DILECTO ET FIDELI.</p>
            <p>So then, if any ſhall enquire in point of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as they did, <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.2. <hi>By what authority you doe theſe things</hi> (I meane <hi>divine:</hi>) Why you, my Lords, examine and give ſentence, the Juſtices here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concurre, the Jurers finde guilty, the Jaylors keepe ſure, the Plaintifs proſecute, and the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners put to death: here is <hi>prima lex ſocietatis, &amp; nervus Imperiorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Carions Chron.</note> the divine Patent or grant, <hi>Whoſo ſheds, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words we have <hi>Authoritatis proſapiam,</hi> the progeny or pedegree, the race or linage, or, if you will, <hi>the Deſcent of Authority</hi> ſet out by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ancient King of Heralds, who hath informed us in all the ancient genealogies. A diſcourſe not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſefull to us all, that Superiors may know how their tenure is but <hi>in capite,</hi> God by a Licence of aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath aſſigned them, and that inferiours may know why they owe <hi>ſuit ſervice</hi> and <hi>homage</hi> to their ſuperiors: becauſe their power ſtands not onely upon the crutches or ſtilts of humane power, but upon the firme baſis of divine inſtitution that ſome ſhould ride on horſe-backe, while others walke on foote.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4558:5"/>
            <p> For the evidencing hereof, obſerve the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The firſt and more generall part of it is laid down, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. and 28. and likewiſe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond verſe of this ninth chapter: <hi>Sciatis quòd aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignavimus vos &amp; quemlibet veſtrum conjunctim &amp; diviſim</hi> to rule over fowles, beaſts, fiſhes. Thus far all mankind hath power. And now in this verſe read, we have <hi>Aſſignavimus etiam vos:</hi> we ſee who are of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> even the Magiſtrates, who have power over men. The like we may read, <hi>Wiſdom</hi> the ninth, from the beginning to the ſeventh verſe. As the Emperour of Germany is ſtiled <hi>Rex Regum:</hi> ſo is a Magiſtrate over men, who are petty Princes over the other creatures. All mankinde are like Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours, all Kings, but the Magiſtrate is <hi>perpetuus Dictator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will be whiſpered by the Temporall power, Trouble not your ſelfe for our Patent further than from our gracious King: we have Jaylers and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, halters and gibbets, axes and ſcaffolds, fire and faggots; we will either finde, or force obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abundans cautela non nocet.</hi> The more tyes, the ſtronger. Mens Lawes may bee ſnapped aſunder more eaſily. Secular lawes and power are but the materials, the hemp or haire: Religion is that which entwines and makes it ſtrong. Men may hope that mans lawes may balke <hi>Agag,</hi> and the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of the people: but Gods Lawes ſay <hi>Quicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que,</hi> they puniſh univerſally. True, the lawes of men are ſtrong, but behold a greater force, a twofold cable. Gods word prevailes more ſtrongly. Where there is either religious devotion, or any melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4558:5"/>jealous fearfulneſſe or ſuſpicion by nature, there is a more ſerious apprehenſion of Gods diſpleaſure than mans. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (a wiſe Teacher) knew what he did, when hee uſed the double two-edged argument, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. <hi>We muſt needs obey, not only for feare of puniſhment, but alſo for conſcience ſake.</hi> Obſerve among the Romiſts: if they can but untie the double knot of conſcience, they care the leſſe for the ſingle tie of corporall puniſhment. Aſſure but <hi>Ravaillac</hi> that it is lawfull to lay his bloudy hands upon the Lords Anoynted, and then he will feare but little hot burning pincers, or the pulling in pieces with wilde horſes. When thoſe moles, the the Gunpowder pioners (following their blinde guides) were conceited that it was not unlawfull to fire that houſe wherein (ſaid they) bloody lawes were made againſt them, they then cared neither for Tyburn nor beheading. And that bloody <hi>Aſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine,</hi> who not many yeares ſince ſlew a great Peere, no doubt but that his bloody mis-led mind thought it lawfull. If Divines do but once file off the fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of divine lawes, men will as faſt ſnap aſunder mens lawes, as <hi>Samſon</hi> did his coards. <hi>Iames Clement,</hi> whom the Leaguers hired to kill <hi>Henry</hi> the third; and <hi>Iohn Chaſtell,</hi> who intended to kill <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, were both taught by the Jeſuites that the King was not to be obeyed, if not allowed by the Pope.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Goodwins An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales, page</hi> 23</note> Inſurrection or rebellion never proves loud or dangerous till it pretend Religion. The firſt noyſe is for the libertie or priviledges of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that is but like the outworkes: but when the ſoule is pretended, that is like the maine fort. They
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4558:6"/>begin thus, The free-born Communaltie is oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a ſmall number: though the calamities of this preſent life may with a conſtant patience bee endured, yet the ſoule is to be redeemed even with a thouſand deaths: new formes of Religion are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded (the conſtant pretence of all diſcontented giddy people.)</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee that the cauſe of Religion, or the tie of conſcience doth move the wheeles of all acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons moſt forcibly. Though it ill becomes them, it is uſually in the mouth of all ſeditious rebels, and then <hi>in nomine Domini</hi> they are moſt violent. The holy league, and holy pilgrimes, and the brethren are uſually the nicknames of rebels.</p>
            <p>Let it not then bee tedious for them who have their Patents ſealed at Weſtminſter, to heare that they are alſo ſealed with a <hi>teſte meipſo</hi> in Heaven. The tye of conſcience looking at Gods ordinance doth helpe to guard Authoritie, as well as the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe with the <hi>poſſe Comitatûs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then you pleaſe to uſher, Preface and auſpicate your waightie affaires with prayers and prayſes here in this ſacred Houſe, after the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all good Chriſtians, holy men in the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; Yea and the devout Heathen alſo, who did uſually begin <hi>à Deo Optimo Maximo:</hi> So you come hither to do him ſervice, to acknowledge your dependance upon him; As a labourer or work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man comes to know his pleaſure that ſets him on worke, ſo you here to be directed by Gods Word. We of our Tribe can do no leſſe but give you your due, namely, that your power ſtands not onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4558:6"/>the ſupporters of mans policy, but the ſtrength of the divine Graunt.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as it is <hi>Pſalme</hi> 45.4. <hi>Good lucke have you with your honour: ride on with the word of truth and righteouſneſſe.</hi> Your Commiſſion is both from God and the King. It is appointed that <hi>Who ſo ſheds mans blood, by man, &amp;c.</hi> as may appeare by the meaning of the words, which come now to bee opened unto us.</p>
            <p>Herein is layd down the juſt power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſword: not excluding Eccleſiaſticall or Oeconomicall, that of parents or maſters; but the publique temporall power is here more principally intended, becauſe it ſpeaks of bloud-ſhed.</p>
            <p>This verſe is ſet like <hi>Bifrons Ianus,</hi> or like <hi>Noah,</hi> who had reference to both Worlds: ſo this verſe is a reaſon both of the former and latter verſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God is carefull to prevent the eating of blood, verſe the 4. that man ſhould have no taſte thereof, and by that abſtinence ſo much the more abhorre murther and crueltie. The reaſon, <hi>whoſo ſheds, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is a reaſon of the 7. verſe. Men may bee encouraged to bring forth fruit and multiply, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath taken ſuch a courſe for our ſafety and preſervation, by pinioning and ſwadling the hands of murtherers. A man may plant, ſet, and ſow in a garden with hope and chearefulneſſe, when it is well fenced, hedged, walled, or empa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. The fortification muſt bee anſwerable to the danger. Murther began betimes, even with <hi>Cain.</hi> God bids <hi>bee fruitfull,</hi> for hee hath taken a courſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4558:7"/>with murtherers, be they high or low, rich or poore: for it is ſaid <hi>Quicunque,</hi> generall and indefinite, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34. <hi>I perceive there is no reſpect of perſons with God:</hi> as hee ſends his raine to fall, and his Sunne to ſhine; ſo hee would have juſtice adminiſterd impartially. <hi>Muſculus</hi> obſerves allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically (but it is ſom-what farfetched) <hi>Of every Beaſt,</hi> ordinary inferiour men that are kept under: or <hi>of man,</hi> that is, bee hee noble, learned, wiſe, or any wayes excellent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sheddeth mans blood,</hi> that is, mortally and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. And here obſerve 3. things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That any kinde of death is here forbidden as well as the effuſion of blood, bee it by poiſoning, ſtrangling, or otherwiſe. A man may ſhed blood and not kill, as Chirurgions: and a man may kill and not ſhed blood, as poyſoners and ſtranglers.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Phlebotomy is not here forbidden, the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or cutting of a veine which is not mortall: but the taking away of life is here ment which lies in the blood, as it is in the fourth verſe. The heart-blood is the ſhop or ſeat of life. Hence it is ſaid, that though the braine be of greater dignity, yet the heart is of greater neceſſity, becauſe it is the fountaine of life.</p>
            <p>No ſhedding of blood (though mortally) is here meant, if it be done by the Magiſtrate agreeably to the lawes of God and men, no more than the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifs, Iurers, Executioners are guilty: for it is ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. The Magiſtrate <hi>beareth not the ſword in vaine.</hi> But private men upon private quarrells are here reſtrained.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Obſerve, that blood-ſhed is here put for it ſelfe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4558:7"/>and other ſinnes: for this power of the Magiſtrate is not reſtrained onely to murther and other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes capitall, yea and to criminall, but to civill alſo. Elſe, there would be no uſe of any Bench, but that which is for life and death. Here then other cauſes are to bee underſtood, although <hi>denominatio fit à principaliori parte.</hi> This maine offence is branded by name, as being inconſiſtent with ſociety. So that this is a principall, not the onely ſinne, for Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to puniſh: as uſually the oath at large is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the fore-man, and all the reſt are implied. Although God be a patient God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.5.</note> yea <hi>the God of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence;</hi> and when wee make bold to expreſſe him by borrowed ſpeeches, we ſay he hath leaden feet, hee came ſoſtly, and convented <hi>Adam</hi> deliberately: yet he will not ſuffer the murtherer to ſtay till the great Aſſizes at Doomes-day, but hee muſt be puniſhed here by his Lieutenant, man. This hatefull ſinne is is named here (we ſee) for all the reſt. When Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had a Viper upon his hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 28.4.</note> the Barbarians cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>No doubt this man is a murtherer.</hi> They thought murder to be the non-ſuch of ſinnes. As <hi>Moſes</hi> here ſets downe the pedegree of Authority: ſo our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſets downe the deſcent of murther, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. He goes higher than <hi>Caine, Yea are of your Father the Devill: he was homicida, a manſlayer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</hi> Let thoſe then who are as prodigall of their owne and others blood as doggs and cockes, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how murther is here branded by name: and ſo it may well be, for it is injurious to five.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To God, whoſe inſtitution is violated, and his image cancelled and defaced.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4558:8"/> 2. To the Magiſtrate, whoſe ſword is taken out of his hand, and hee made like the ſigne of Saint <hi>George.</hi> If a man be injured, are there not Courts of juſtice, both for our profit &amp; for our honour? What nonſenſe then is it, for a man in rage or paſſion, which is a ſhort madneſſe, when hee is not his owne man, that hee ſhould wreſt the ſword out of the hands of the ſober, juſt, deliberate Magiſtrate, and revenge his quarrell himſelfe?</p>
            <p n="3">3. A murcherer is injurious incomparably to that man whom he ſlayes, ſo as he cannot give him ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction If he take away his goods, he might reſtore: if his good name, hee might recant: but who can fetchbacke a departed ſoule? he onely can give life that firſt infuſed it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A murtherer is injurious to himſelfe. 1. To his body, making it liable to a violent death: or his life afterwards (if his conſcience be not aſleepe) is a continuall Purgatorie, as wee may obſerve in ſome who have beene heires to <hi>Cain's</hi> murther, they have been likewiſe inheritors of his deſpicable wofull wandring. 2 For his ſoule, he cannot ſay at his death with our Saviour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 154. <hi>ad Publicol.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſummatum eſt:</hi> for without bitter repentance hee leapes out of the pan into the fire. Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth ſo diſlike man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, that he ſaith <hi>non ſibiprobari illud conſilium, ut quiſpiam alium interficiat, nè ab illo occidatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. A blood-ſhedder mortally and wilfully is inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to his wife and children, by forfaiting his eſtate, and depriving them of that which ſhould be for their comfortable livelihood and maintenance. <hi>Thomas Aquinas of every beaſt</hi> expounds it <hi>of beaſtly men,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4558:8"/>that murtherers are metaphorically like beaſts, raſh, violent, furious, inconſiderate, cruell, unreaſonable, and unprovident as they.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that Gods Spirit by <hi>Moſes</hi> hath ſtig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized this hatefull vice, let not raſh anger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, malice and revenge proſecute, and a vaine conceit of honour occaſion the committing of this deſperate ſinne, which God will not have ſtay till the day of Doom, but bee puniſhed by his Deputy, Man: which word now followes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By man.</hi> Wee muſt not ſtraiten theſe words as confined to <hi>Noah</hi> and his immediate ſucceſſours; but as the priviledges and juriſdiction in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of mankinde over other creatures, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the power of man one over another doth ſtill continue.</p>
            <p>Againe, wee muſt not thinke that <hi>by man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Providet nè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terficiant iuſſu non expectato publico.</hi> Aug. <hi>in</hi> Exod.</note> the Magiſtrate is to be ſo underſtood, as if they were to be the Executioners, &amp; ſo condemne under-officers; for they are the Magiſtrates hands.</p>
            <p>Theſe words, <hi>by man,</hi> are rarely left out, uſually put in, alwayes underſtood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By man, the Magiſtrate;</hi> ſo the Chaldee Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe, <hi>per ſententiam Iudicum,</hi> and ſo <hi>Cornelius à Lapide</hi> upon theſe words quotes it, and expounds it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> acknowledgeth the Magiſtrates autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to bee hence derived, <hi>ſed verba plus complecti dicit. By man,</hi> the Magiſtrate disjunctively, or ſome other way by man. For it is ſaid, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 55.23. <hi>Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty men ſhall not live out halfe their dayes.</hi> So that if the murtherer eſcape by flight, or that the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate be too remiſſe or indulgent, yet either in war
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4558:9"/>or quarrell, duell or other caſualtie the murtherers life is taken away.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Iunius</hi> expounds theſe words <hi>by man</hi> in his Analyſis of this chapter. Hee ſaith there are lawes, 1. naturall, of the creatures ſubjection, verſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond 2. ceremoniall, verſe the fourth, forbidding blood-eating 3. civill and politicall, verſe the ſixth, <hi>quum Deus manum ſui Magiſtratûs inſtruit ad ulciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Muſculus</hi> gives an unanſwerable reaſon, why <hi>by man</hi> we are to underſtand <hi>the Magiſtrate.</hi> If a private man kill the murtherer, and another private man him, and ſo <hi>in infinitum,</hi> what will become of the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of mankinde? God therefore deputes the Magiſtrate to doe it, and there's an end. Neither (ſaith the ſame Author) is this a fault in the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, to uſe a ſword either defenſive or offenſive to malefactors. It is not ſaid <hi>Quicunque effuderit ſanguinem homicidae, latronis, venefici, &amp;c.</hi> for theſe putrified members muſt either be taken away, or they endanger the whole.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercer</hi> ſaith, <hi>not by private men, nè niſi maturè &amp; cauſâ diligenter excuſsâ occidatur.</hi> If it were left to private men, in their choler they would put to death without juſt cauſe, as in <hi>chance-medly</hi> or <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure,</hi> which the Magiſtrate doth not puniſh with death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> here underſtands <hi>the Magiſtrate,</hi> and makes the later words a comment or reaſon. <hi>Quia illum fecit (ſcilicet Magiſtratum) ad imaginem Dei; &amp; non</hi> HOMINES, <hi>ſed</hi> ELOHIM <hi>appellantur.</hi> God borrowes the word <hi>King,</hi> ſtiling himſelfe <hi>King of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4558:9"/>Kings,</hi> and for an abundant requitall lends Kings the title of <hi>Gods.</hi> Though all men are created after Gods image: yet thoſe that are in authoritie have a more ſpeciall reſemblance of the Deity. All men of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, learning, wealth, and other abilities, are as bullion: but the Magiſtrate hath the very currant ſtamp of Gods power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piſcator</hi> alſo herein concurres, QVI EFFVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIT, <hi>nempe privato affectu, ex odio aut ira:</hi> PER HOMINEM, <hi>ideſt, Magiſtratum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have endevoured (you heare) to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation ſtrong, becauſe we are to build much here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, Gods Patent to his Deputies, or the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent of Authority.</p>
            <p>It followes, <hi>ſhal his blood be ſhed.</hi> God proportions his puniſhments. <hi>Blood for blood,</hi> as it is <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.23. or, <hi>Life for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus We ſee the divine juſtice paying murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in their owne coyn: <hi>Occidit &amp; occidatur. Ole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after</hi> ſaith upon theſe words, <hi>A principio Mundi oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſio occiſione vindicatur.</hi> This retaliation of blood for blood Chriſt told Saint <hi>Peter</hi> of, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.52. <hi>Whoſe killeth with the ſword, ſhall periſh by the ſword.</hi> The ſame words are uſed <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.10. here is <hi>Lex talionis.</hi> They that account the life of another cheap, do make the market and price for their own.</p>
            <p>From theſe words, thus opened, theſe divine truths preſent themſelves to our conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Whoſoever,</hi> that God is impartiall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sheds mans blood,</hi> The hainouſneſſe of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here named.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>By man,</hi> The Deſcent of Authority.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:4558:10"/> 4. <hi>Shall his blood be ſhed,</hi> The proportioning of Gods puniſhments to mans ſinnes.</p>
            <p>But as I made choice of theſe words for this time and place: ſo I will inſiſt onely in the third and moſt uſefull to us, the <hi>terminus à quo</hi> of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or the Deſcent of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maſter Harding,</hi> to ſet the Crowne the faſter upon the Popes head, is content that it ſhould ſtand but totteringly upon the heads of temporall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as if no hand could ſet it on faſt, but that of the Biſhop of Rome. And therefore he ſaith moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly, that they can have no more power than the people had over whom they exerciſe their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction: as if they had no other right, but by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition from their ſubjects; forgetting theſe places, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>By mee Kings raigne.</hi> And againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating it twice, <hi>By mee Princes rule.</hi> And <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.21. <hi>He removes and ſets up Kings,</hi> without the Pope his intervening. His uſurpation was not heard of till many yeares after. To the like effect ſpake our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to <hi>Pilate, Iohn</hi> 19.11. <hi>Thou couldſt have no power at al, except it were given thee from above</hi> Thus S. <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>There is no power but of God.</hi> Which made him recant, as it were, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.5. <hi>I wiſt not that it was the high Prieſt: For it is written,</hi> (namely <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28.) <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods,</hi> (for ſo it is rendred in the laſt Tranſlation) this phraſe being given to Magiſtrates: and perhaps from hence the Heathen worſhipped mortall Gods. <hi>Cyrus</hi> is ſaid to be Gods anoynted, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 4 5.1. In the firſt part of the <hi>Homily againſt wilfull rebellion</hi> it is ſaid, ſince Lucifer the Arch-rebel, and our firſt parents in Paradiſe broke
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4558:10"/>the bonds of duty, God hath eſtabliſhed authority, firſt in families, then in Cities, Townes, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. Even ſubordinate Authority is from God, though like coſen-germane it be once removed from God and the King. Yea Magiſtrates in little Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Iuriſdictions, they are the younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Authority: there is the ſame blood, though not the ſame ſplendour or revenue. The varniſh or gilt of power is the ſame, though the walls or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls bee finer or courſer. <hi>Caeſars</hi> image, or the Kings ſtampe makes ſilver as currant as gold.</p>
            <p>And this Deſcent may appeare or be vouched,</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the excellency, uſe, and benefit of it, as it is ſaid, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17. <hi>Every good and perfect gift comes downe from above.</hi> Now this is the very <hi>ſine qua non</hi> of ſociety and outward bleſſings; not onely for the <hi>bene eſſe,</hi> but for the very <hi>eſſe</hi> of a Common-Wealth: without this people are like a riotous rout in warre without leaders in order, as ſheepe without a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, or a body without an head.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Deſcent appeares by Gods admirable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding &amp; continuing it, maugre mans reluctations; God preſerves ſtill the ceremony and the ſubſtance. Firſt, thoſe additions of ceremony, which makes it have the more due valuation from the people, as Crownes, Thrones, Scepters, Attenders, great Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, for the ſupreme; and Gownes, Tippets, Hoods, Maces, Swords, White ſtaves, caps of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, for the ſubordinate Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>And as the ceremony, ſo the ſubſtance of it is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held: and this God doth 4. wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By his Word, as you have heard out of S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4558:11"/>the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> &amp; other teſtimonies of Scripture.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By his Spirit to Godly men, and by the inſtinct and dictate of nature to Heathen and ungodly men; not to hurt Authority though they have opportunitie. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. obſerve <hi>Davids</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpeech, and more excellent carriage to <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was in the cave in his power, although <hi>Saul</hi> did proſecute him cauſeleſly, implacably, and infinitly. And although ſome men quarrell ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at <hi>Magiſtatum</hi> the perſon; yet not at <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratum,</hi> the government: their deſires are not to dull or breake the ſword, but onely to change the hand, as uſually reſtleſſe giddy people do, like them in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.19. <hi>Nay, but wee will have a King to reigne over us,</hi> as they would exchange their Iudges for Kings. <hi>Ketts</hi> and <hi>Flammocks,</hi> with ſuch other viperous rebels, their projects are not to extinguiſh government, but to exchange Governours, putting themſelves or their leaders in place. And ſtill our mutterers and raſh diſcontented people, their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell is not ſo much againſt Authority it ſelfe: but if they bee inferiors, it is becauſe they have none themſelves, they will give no applauſe to the actors, becauſe they beare no part themſelves. And if they bee of an higher ſtraine, it is becauſe they may not rule their Rulers. So that as a coy dame or amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woer, they muſt have clothes, but no taylour can fitt them: either the garment of Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is too long or ſhort, too ſtraight or wide. As a ſick man muſt drinke, yet all is inſipid; no cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor bed gives him content: yet the fault is not in the things themſelves, but in his indiſpoſition.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4558:11"/>Vſually they that are diſcontented at Governours, it is becauſe themſelves or ſome of their friends are not in higher place. As all mankind acknowledge a Deity, yet goe ſeverall wayes in their devotions: So all by nature and the Spirit of God are taught the admirable uſe of Authority, although they be affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed divers waies for Governours and government, according as their owne ends leade them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God upholds &amp; preſerves Authority by his wife, faithfull, godly Miniſters. Even our poore Tribe helpeth to carry the Canopy over Authority: elſe, what need our Declarations ſometimes at S. <hi>Pauls Croſſe,</hi> or other ſolemn places, to juſtifie the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of State in matters of conſcience? Thus you ſhal find wiſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> Biſhop of the <hi>Cretians,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1.</note> Put them in minde to be ſubject to Principalities and Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to obey Magiſtrates.</hi> And thus our prudent Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their Commiſſioners doe inquire in the Articles at their Viſitations; <hi>Doth your Minister exhort the people to obedience to his Majeſtie, and all Magiſtrates in authority under him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. Boys in his <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pag 458.</note> Even ſtatizing worldlings that account but ſlightly of us, yet think that we ſerve as poſts at leaſt upon which the Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions &amp; Mandates of the Magiſtrates are to be fixed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. God preſerves Authority by his admirable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and prevention of wicked plots againſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors and Government. As Murthers have been ſtrangely revealed by Birds, &amp; Dogs; ſo even wicked intendments againſt Magiſtrates have beene wonderfully diſcloſed, not onely miraculouſly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, as it is ſet downe, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.29, 30. <hi>If theſe men die a common death, &amp;c. But if the Lord make
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4558:12"/>a new thing, yee ſhall underſtand that theſe men have provoked the Lord;</hi> Intimating, that God will mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly puniſh rebellion. The very patient Earth, the hackney of all injurious trampling, will open her mouth and ſwallow them up.</p>
            <p>As God miraculouſly puniſheth, ſo he alſo diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth rebellions and treacheries. <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought: for the birds of the Aire will reveale it.</hi> Thus carefull is God to preſerve his of-ſpring, both the perſon and the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Now as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39. <hi>If it be of God, it will continue: if not, it will come to nought.</hi> If Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority were onely humane pride, or invention, it would long before now have had a fall. It is worth our remembrance,
<note place="margin">Theatre of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> that by conſpiracies Magiſtrates are ſeldome hurt, and as ſeldome the conſpiratours eſcape: as is obſerved in <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, <hi>Num.</hi> 16. of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. and many others. In the time of that wiſe King who conjoyned the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, inſurrection was (if not a quotidian) an anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary feaver: yet as he was ever moleſted, ſo hee was ever aloft and prevailed. The like was in the time of our late gracious Queene, and peaceable King, by the powder-plotters and others.</p>
            <p>And when it pleaſeth God rarely to let the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſuffer for the puniſhment of the people, yet thoſe rebels are ſo hatefull to God and all good men, as makes the like courſes abhorred for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo Authority to be preſerved and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> uſed to ſay, <hi>Proditionem amo, proditores non item. Charles</hi> the fourth, Emperour of Germany, prevailed with three or foure of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4558:12"/>enemies Captaines to be perfidious to their Maſter, upon hopes of great ſummes of money: and when he ſped, he paid them with counterfait coyne, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it to be good enough for counterfait ſervice.</p>
            <p>When the city of <hi>Rhodes</hi> was beſieged by the Turke, a Noble man, upon hopes to have one of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lymans</hi> daughters, did many ſecret ſervices for the Turke perfidiouſly againſt his owne City: which when <hi>Solyman</hi> wonne, hee cauſed the treacherous man to be flayed alive, ſaying it was not lawfull for a Chriſtian to marry a Turke, except hee put off his old skin. And that <hi>Baniſter,</hi> who treacherouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed his Lord and Maſter; when he expected his thouſand pounds, King <hi>Richard</hi> gave him not a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ſaying, that hee who would bee untrue to ſo good a Maſter, muſt needs be falſe to all others. In our Law <hi>crimen laeſae Majeſtatis</hi> is accounted ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous an offence, to conſpire againſt the breath of him who is the breath of our noſtrills, as that it is no plea for him that is <hi>non compos mentis,</hi> although it be for ordinary homicide. And in the ſtate oeconomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, murther committed by one that is in ſubjection, is accounted petty treaſon: ſo hatefull by the lawes of God and man is diſobedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Why doth the omnipotent God depute fraile men to be his Lieutenants? why not an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, or a legion of his powerfull heavenly attendants or pages?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That the excellency of the ſucceſſe may be aſcribed to God, where it is due, and not to men, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Wee have this treaſure in earthen veſſels.</hi> When we daily ſee ſtrong ſinnes pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4558:13"/>downe by the preaching of weake men, we juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude, that it is the power of God accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying his ordinance. And when wee obſerve that men Magiſtrates, and not Angels, do ſway the world, quelling and captivating daring vices, wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be Gods power. If Magiſtrates were like Angels, of miraculous power; like <hi>Argus,</hi> one of them to have an hundred eyes, or, as <hi>Briareus,</hi> an hundred hands; which they have indeed virtually, not formally; if every one of them were as rich and wiſe as <hi>Salomon,</hi> or ſtrong as <hi>Sampſon,</hi> or that they could deſtroy mankinde, as the Angel did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventie thouſand amongſt the Iſraelites, wee might thinke it was their own power. But now we ſee it is a ſecret vertue in the divine ordinance. An horſe hath ſtrength enough to caſt his rider, and runne away from him, but doth not uſually. And as ſtrong oxen are guided by little children, in regard of the image of God in mankinde: thus are a multitude of ſtrong and violent people ruled by Magiſtracy; not onely for feare of puniſhment, but even for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake.</p>
            <p>This reaſon is given by God himſelfe, <hi>Iudges</hi> 7.2. <hi>The people are too many: leſt Iſrael vaunt, ſaying, mine owne hand hath ſaved me.</hi> So if Angels ruled, it would bee judged to be by their owne power. But God for his owne glory hath appointed men of the ſame mold, of the ſame ſtuffe by nature, borne and dye alike, uſually better qualified with experience, learning, wiſedome, and integrity: yet they are but men, and in the judgement of raſh ſelf-conceited by-ſtanders, not better qualified than others; for in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4558:13"/>their ſimple judgement they thinke they ſee more than the gameſters. God, I ſay, for his owne glory doth hang great plummets upon weake lines, as in the Miniſtery, ſo in the Magiſtracy, that God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch ſtrong effects by weake cauſes, we may ſay, as it is <hi>Pſalme</hi> 115.1. <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, but unto thy name, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. God deputes mankinde, not Angels, <hi>ex gratia,</hi> it being a great favour, firſt, to the party injured. Secondly, to the party injuring. Thirdly, to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, the party puniſhing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to the party injured, for the propinquity. As the Scripture ſaith, <hi>yee need not go to Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut</hi> 30.18.</note> nor to the deepe, but the word is neare thee:</hi> So may wee ſay of government, (eſpecially in theſe itinerary cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits) Iuſtice is adminiſtred even at our doores.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to the party to be puniſhed, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 20.19. <hi>Speake thou with us, but let not God ſpeake, leſt we die.</hi> If God ſhould pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh by extraordinary judgements, as the Egyptians; or with miraculous plagues, as he did to <hi>Corah</hi> and the like, it would be moſt terrible to malefactors: whereas now being by men, they may parly for their lives, they muſt be caſt or acquitted by their Peeres or equals.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to the Magiſtrate. As he hath made him his Deputy, ſo he puts valuation upon him by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying him. And thereby he doth quicken in men induſtry, paines, and care, that they may come to be Magiſtrates, that is, ſublimated manhood. God as the Sun, doth irradiate Magiſtracy as the Moone, with his brightneſſe. As Chriſt was himſelfe bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4558:14"/>but never baptized any, and gave the Euchariſt but once, to put a valuation upon his ordinance in the hands of the Miniſters. So in the Magiſtracy he graces his Deputy, Man, putting the honour and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment upon him. It is ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.8. <hi>The mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes ſaw it, and glorified God which had given ſuch power unto men.</hi> As there for miracles, ſo here for authority. If <hi>David</hi> did breake out ſo pathetically, <hi>O Lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.4.</note> what is man! Thou haſt made him Lord,</hi> &amp;c. How much more may wee ſay, <hi>Lord, what is a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, that thou doſt thus advance him,</hi> even over men!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. Doth not God challenge authority to be his Domaine? which he will not let out, but keep in his own hands, ſaying, as it is, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 32.35. which is quoted by Saint <hi>Paul, Rom</hi> 12.9. <hi>Vengeance is mine, I will repay.</hi> Whereupon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> makes his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Alexander did me much evill, the Lord reward him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By theſe places it is meant that private men muſt not uſurpe: for elſe, what God doth by his Deputies, he doth it as it were by himſelfe. As the Lord Keeper writes <hi>teſte meipſo;</hi> and the Iudges of other Courts, and the Iuſtices may write <hi>Carolus Dei,</hi> &amp;c. noting in whoſe right and power they doe it. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> diſclaimes it onely as being a private man. God will hereafter avenge, <hi>Niſi priùs Iuſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arii venerint, &amp;c.</hi> and in the meane time he doth it by them as his Subſtitutes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. But is not this old Grant out of date? Are not Chriſtian Magiſtrates put out of Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Chriſts comming.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:4558:14"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thus thinke the Anabaptiſts, whoſe obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions <hi>Zanchius</hi> well anſwers, urging Chriſts ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>Pilate,</hi> Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> appealing to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the other Apoſtles clearing themſelves, but yet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the Magiſtrates, acknowledging the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be of God.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Deſcent of Authority</hi> may teach us:</p>
            <p>Firſt, To take notice of that Jeſuiticall doctrine and practice to lay violent hands upon Gods De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties upon a pretence of Religion. Murther, as you have heard, is a moſt wicked ſinne, and diſobedience is as the ſin of witchcraft. Now treaſon is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting or putting together both theſe ſinnes. The old warrantable doctrine and practice of the Church in the primitive times was, prayers unto, and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations for the Governours. This was the Churches force, both defenſive and offenſive: and ſtill with all godly learned Chriſtians it is concluded,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Epiſe. Daven. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Renuente Principe populus non debet moliri Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Like unto theſe, but not ſo ill, are thoſe that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence with their tongues, though not with their hands: ſuch as are diſreſpective to them that are in authority, not ſpeaking of them, or to them, publickly or privately, as to Gods Vicegerents, but with quips and girds, to pleaſe themſelves, and to ſtroke the people. This is rather like unto Satyricall Poets, than anſwerable to Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> advice, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but intreat him as a father.</hi> And like his doctrine was his practice to <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Feſtus:</hi> and thus was the Prophet <hi>Daniels</hi> to the Aſſyrian and Perſian Kings.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4558:15"/>
            <p> Contrary to theſe holy men are thoſe monſters in a Kingdome, who endeavour by all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to enervate and weaken Authority, thereby to make it contemptible. God caſts his divine luſtre upon them, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was when he had beene talking with God:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> of Hereticks.</note> And theſe; as <hi>Moles,</hi> are alwaies vexing and diſturbing firme ground, blinde without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and deſpicable when their plots are diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
            <p>Let none then in Pulpits or Parlours deprave Governours and government: if they doe, thoſe words, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.7. may bee truly applied to them, <hi>Ye take too much upon you.</hi> Authority is Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and muſt not bee made unſavory by finding and creating faults in Governours. It is ſtrange, that they who would be accounted the children of God, doe not digeſt the Deputies of God: for they have beene, are, and (it is to be feared) ever will bee op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite and Antipodes to all Governours, both Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall and Civill.</p>
            <p>They will ſay,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Our quarrell is not againſt govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the faults of Governours:</hi> and they thinke with <hi>Abſalom, Oh if they were in place, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the common hackney pretence or colour.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> But let theſe mote-finders conſider, that Magiſtrates in a Common-wealth are like parents in an houſe, politicall fathers. Is it fit for a ſonne to bee like <hi>Cham?</hi> Though the father bee guilty, ſhall a ſonne talke of nothing but his fathers faults, diſcovering his fathers nakedneſſe, eſpecially when this ſonne himſelfe is idle and diſobedient? Will ſome men, like children, nothing but eat, drinke, ſleepe, play,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4558:15"/>(indeed there is little elſe expected of them) and yet like fell, ill conditioned children, will they cry, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, and diſturbe others? Let theſe ſonnes of Belial, who cannot beare the yoke of Governours, bee examined in their private vocations, how lazy, how oppreſſing, and how unprofitable to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World. Theſe people are like <hi>Chorus</hi> upon the Stage: being private men, and their wings too big for their neſts, and their feet for their ſhooes, they deſire ſtill to roule and enlarge themſelves as ſnow-balls, and like the Babel-builders, will make themſelves a turret or pillar by popularity Tell me, vaine diſturber, how wouldſt thou like a ſervant thus qualified, to ſay, my maſter is unfit for his place: he is ſilly, ignorant, negligent, or the like: he doth not as a maſter ſhould doe. True indeed, hee doth not, if hee ſuffer without puniſhment ſuch a ſaucy ſervant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Deſcent of Authority may teach us how neare of Kindred Magiſtrates and Miniſters are: the one is <hi>Dei gratiâ,</hi> &amp; the other is <hi>providentiâ divinâ:</hi> ſometimes they are inherent in the ſame perſon. Our bleſſed Saviour was both a King and a Prieſt, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were both victorious Magiſtrates and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Prophets. And if they bee not joyntly in one perſon, yet wee ſee they are brethren, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Lot,</hi> proceeding from the ſame ſpring-head: celeſtiall, God; terreſtriall, the King. And this the later end of an Act of Parliament intimates for the uniformity of Common prayer: If the Ordinary have puniſhed, then not the temporall power: and if not that, then the Ordinary. If either puniſh, it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4558:16"/>becauſe both come from the ſame fountaine.</p>
            <p>For us in our Pulpits, to ſlight this high ordinance, were as great indiſcretion, as for the Magiſtrates up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Benches to diſparage our Profeſſion. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt Magiſtrates may bee capable of the juſt reproofe of the Clergie, and the Clergy of the juſt cenſure of the Magiſtracy. But all muſt take heed, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they can, that neither of their excellent Callings ſuffer by it. The people will neglect both, if they doe not protect us from injuries: and wee teach the people conſcionably to obey them.</p>
            <p>Magiſtrates are Gods Deputies, and Miniſters his <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. As it is ſaid in another caſe, <hi>Ruth</hi> 4.11. theſe two like <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah</hi> do build up the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Panermitan.</hi> Sir <hi>John Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deridge.</hi>
                  </note> conjunctim</hi> better than <hi>diviſim. Theologia &amp; Ius</hi> muſt <hi>fraternizare.</hi> They both looke at the ſame end, namely rectifying of the manners. Both <hi>Moſes</hi> his hands muſt be held up, that vicious <hi>Amaleck</hi> may be pulled downe. If the ſinews of government bee ſlackned by inconſiderate Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and that they doe not uphold one another, as the Elme the Vine, ſinne and vice will more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thruſt in.</p>
            <p>But when Magiſtrates, Chriſts Subſtitutes in his Kingly Office; and the Miniſters, Chriſts Subſtitutes in his Prieſtly Office; ſtay one another, as buttreſſes below or ſpars above: then the temporall ſword cuts deepe in the outward man, and the ſpirituall in the conſcience.</p>
            <p>Wee are all Miniſters of God, both Magiſtrates and Prieſts. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> intimates, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſpeaking of the Magiſtrate: which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4558:16"/>word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is commonly uſed for our Tribe, as <hi>Philp.</hi> 1.1. <hi>With the Biſhops and Deaecons:</hi> and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Deacons muſt be the husbands of one wife.</hi> This is a part of the Epiſtle when Deacons are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into Orders.</p>
            <p>If the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> then be uſed for them both, becauſe they are imployed to doe ſervice for one Maſter, let them not counter-worke one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: but as the walls uphold the roofe, and the roofe keepes drie the walls; ſo ſhould theſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances aſſiſt one another; that the temporall power may regulate the outward man, words and actions; &amp; the ſpiritual ſword the inuer man, thoughts &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Thoſe that would occaſion any civill warre or breach betwixt theſe two, endeavour to diſable thoſe ſhores that beare them up. It is great raſhneſſe for ſome unadviſed Teachers, and diſcontented peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, like themſelves, who love to dance after their ill tuned pipes, to be alwaies throwing dirt into the faces of Governours and government: being private men they hate and envie all thoſe that have power.</p>
            <p>An eminent Prelate of our Church ſaid in his Sermon to the Parliament, <hi>The Church cannot dwell but in the State, nor the Common-wealth flouriſh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church. When the Church, the houſe of grace, is a welcome inmate to the State, which is a wiſe fabrick of policy,</hi> not onely humane, but a divine ordinance. In a word, let theſe ordinances, like husband &amp; wife, live with harmony and love together. The ſoule cannot act <hi>(quoad nos)</hi> but by the body, nor the body live without the ſoule: ſo theſe ordinances.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and in briefe, leſt I bee injurious to your
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4558:17"/>imployments whileſt I plead for them, this may be uſefull both to Superiours and inferiours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to Magiſtrates and Superiours. My Lords and others, give me leave onely to put you in minde of the pedegree or Deſcent of your Authority. It is from above, from God, of the blood Royall, both from another, and for another. As a Nobleman doth or ſhould endeavour to imitate the vertues of him that raiſed his houſe: ſo let Magiſtrates carriage not be bitter or inſipid, but ſweet, pure, cleane, like the fountaine from whence it came. They muſt not be like old courtiers or rich citizens, forgetting from whence they had their beginning. A man in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is not <hi>genus generaliſſimum, quo nihil ſuperius:</hi> as he is <hi>genus hujus,</hi> ſo he is <hi>ſpecies illius,</hi> like the Moon, borrowing light from the Sun; they muſt not, as butchers or graziers, then, judge by the feeling only, but all their proceedings muſt reſemble that image and ſuperſcription which it hath from the great <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> the Lord chiefe Juſtice of Heaven and Earth. They muſt like rivers returne tribute and homage to that Ocean whence their power commeth. They muſt doe better than private men for example ſake, more good and leſſe evill, conſidering their high deſcent and Anceſtours, whom they muſt labour to reſemble ſo farre as humane infirmitie will permit, by endeavouring to be holy, juſt, mercifull, imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, wiſe, deliberate, as he is from whom they derive their power. I might eaſily be large in ſhewing that God is ſo, and that his Deputies ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>Yea further, Let all, even inferiour Officers, and Jurors, and whoſoever beare any part in the puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4558:17"/>of ſinne; let them labour to bee juſt and free from any ſharking or oppreſſion. We finde that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is of an excellent race, nobly deſcended; and therefore it ſhould be generous, not making the vigour and power of Authority to be onely a <hi>modus acquirendi,</hi> like the Publicans. It was lawfull to pay tribute to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> our Saviour did not gainſay it, but bid <hi>Render unto Caeſar.</hi> And he told Saint <hi>Peter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth</hi> 22.21 <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27.</note> Leſt we ſhould give offence, though the children be free, yet take twentie pence for thee and me.</hi> But then the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans made that bitter or harſh, which would other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have been better digeſted: becauſe they did not onely take for their maſters, like tame hawkes, but like wilde hawkes ſnatched alſo for themſelves Such were the toll-gatherers or receivers of the publike revenue for the Romanes amongſt the Jews: who, becauſe they gathered publike payments, were termed <hi>Publicans.</hi> Although their calling was good,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10.</note> and ſome of their perſons good (witneſſe our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours converſing with them, and the Publican pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Phariſee, and <hi>Zacheus</hi> who was <hi>Princip<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Publicanorum:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 19.2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.9.</note> Matthew</hi> the Publicane was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an Apoſtle) yet their imployment was not very acceptable. People were then ſlow in paying publike money: and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen the gatherers oppreſſions, and private exactions over and above their maſters dues, made them more hard of digeſtion. <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports of one <hi>Sabinus,</hi> that had a monument for him with this inſcription, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for a faich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Publicane: as if that were a great commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſidering that <hi>occaſiones faciunt latrones.</hi> But let men in authority, from the higheſt to the loweſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4558:18"/>prove the deſcent of their power by its juſtice and generoſity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let people learne from hence to acknowledg this Deſcent of Authority, and that therefore they muſt neither uſurp it, nor ſlight it, nor diſobey it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, not uſurp it. They muſt ſtay for a lawfull calling: private men and women muſt onely act in their owne ſpheres and circuits, as Maſters over ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and parents over children. Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit was troubled in him at the idolatrie of the Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>cts</hi> 17.16.</note> but being a private man he onely exhorted, but did nothing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, People muſt not ſlight it, becauſe it is ſo nobly borne, as appeares by this Heraldry booke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> where we finde, as it is <hi>Act.</hi> 19.35. that this goddeſſe Magiſtracy is that image of power which is come downe from Heaven. Being ſo highly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, it is <hi>ſcandalum Magnatum</hi> to ſpeake ſlightly of it. And it is highly imployed alſo: for either of theſe wayes may this fault be committed. Magiſtracy hath the priviledges both waies; being highly born, as Nobles; and highly imployed, as great Officers.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We muſt obey and ſubmit to this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, even for conſcience ſake. Take Saint <hi>Peters</hi> advice, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14 which is a part of the Epiſtle appointed to bee read the twentie ſeventh day of this moneth, the day of our gracious King his entry to the Kingdome, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man for the Lords ſake: whether it bee to the King, as ſupreme; or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him.</hi> For the Lords ſake, the Founder of it; and for its owne ſake, being ſo incomparably
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4558:18"/>beneficiall for people. Not to eſteeme of theſe and obey them, as Gods Deputies, is a kind of civill A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme. For we may ſay juſtly as the people to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> unjuſtly, <hi>The ordinance of God and not of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that wee may the better ſubmit,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 12.22.</note> take theſe helpes following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Make it not our imployment to finde and make faults in Governours. For then out of envie we ſhall thinke them faulty without cauſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.15. <hi>I have beene no waies injurious to them.</hi> Indeed hee had meekely, juſtly, and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly brought them out of the land of <hi>Egypt:</hi> yet obſerve in the third verſe <hi>Corah</hi> and his company quarrelled, <hi>Why lift ye your ſelves above the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord?</hi> And though the patient Earth mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly puniſhed them, yet in the 41. verſe all the multitude murmured, ſaying, <hi>Ye have killed, &amp;c.</hi> And then God ſlew more of them. Magiſtrates and Miniſters are like cities upon hils, all eyes are fixed &amp; obſerving them. They cannot poſſibly avoyd this <hi>dilemma,</hi> fork, or crotch from peeviſh, cenſorious by-ſtanders. If they be quick and active, then they are buſie and cruell: if mercifull and gentle, then they are dull, lazy, and remiſſe in their places. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt came neither eating nor drinking,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.18, 19.</note> and they ſaid he had a Devill. The Sonne of man came ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking, and they ſaid, Behold a glutton and a wine-bibber.</hi> If a Governour bee like <hi>Solomon</hi> taking care for the building of a Temple, the fruits of peace and devotion: yet the people will ſay,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7.</note> as it is 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 10 4. <hi>The yoke is grievous.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> being an active man, conquering the Jebuſites, hee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4558:19"/>is accounted <hi>Vir ſanguinum.</hi> For as the Sea, though of it ſelfe indifferently quiet, yet there are ever and anon ſome whiſtling winds to make it troubleſome: So there are alwaies ſome like <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> who ſtroke the people with cavils againſt Governours, thereby to ſowre and leaven them. From which cenſorious conceits proceed daring ſpeeches;
<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Lord <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lam</hi> in <hi>Hen.</hi> 7.</note> And <hi>liberty of ſpeech, it is the female of Sedition,</hi> and in time the Grand-mother of treaſon. Take heed of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching arguments; Romiſts on the one ſide; and the miſcalled <hi>Sions Plea,</hi> and the like, on the other: by which under a cloake of Religion they labour to make the people diſaffected to their Governours and government.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Remember whence Magiſtrates come. Looke upon them, not perſonally, but relatively. When an Ambaſſadour comes, wee doe not preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire or prie how learned, rich, wiſe, or nobly borne hee is, but from what a great Maſter hee comes and doth repreſent. <hi>Alexander</hi> would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the ſonne of a God, thereby to keepe his people in obedience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Doe as ye would be done by. How would ye have your children and ſervants carry themſelves in your private families? Not uſurpe, nor ſleight, nor diſobey you. And if ye come to any publike imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, would ye have them that are under you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve nothing but your warpings and failings, yea worſe, creating jealouſies and ſuſpicions without cauſe? <hi>Lycurgus</hi> being asked why the government was not popular, anſwered, <hi>Tu prius in domo tua efficito principatum popularem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4558:19"/> 4. Conſider that the worſt kind of Governours or Government is better than an Anarchy: And therefore that Magiſtracy is a great bleſſing, being the very life of ſociety. No marvell then that Saint <hi>Iude</hi> reckoneth <hi>ſpeaking ill of dignities</hi> among great faults.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Forget not Gods command, <hi>Honour thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c.</hi> not onely Naturall, but Politicall; thy father in the kingdome, as well as in the family: <hi>that thy dayes may be long;</hi> being peaceable ſubjects here, and glorious citizens hereafter: the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is <hi>parens patriae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Pray to God, who doth diſpoſe the hearts of Rulers and people; that the one may governe, and the other obey conſcionably, uſing theſe and the like prayers, with which I will conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Almighty God, whoſe Kingdome is everlaſting, and power infinite, have mercy upon the whole congregation, and ſo rule the heart of thy choſen ſervant</hi> Charles, <hi>our King and Governour, and the hearts of all that are in authority under him, that they knowing whoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters they are, may above all things ſeeke thy honour and glory: and that we duely conſidering whoſe authority they have (as wee have beene taught) may faithfully ſerve, honour, and humbly obey them, in thee and for thee, according to thy bleſſed Word and Ordinance through Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
